<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<osis xmlns="http://www.bibletechnologies.net/2003/OSIS/namespace" TEIform="TEI.2">
  <osisText xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" canonical="true" osisIDWork="kjv-apocrypha" osisRefWork="Bible" xml:lang="en" xml:space="default" TEIform="text">
    <header TEIform="teiHeader" canonical="false">
      <revisionDesc TEIform="revisionDesc">
        <date event="eversion" type="ISO" xml:lang="en" TEIform="date">2025.08.10T13:29:30</date>
        <p TEIform="p">Scraped from www.pseudepigrapha.com/apocrypha_ot, and converted to OSIS by the osis-kjv-apocrypha Python package.</p>
      </revisionDesc>
      <work osisWork="King James Version Apocrypha">
        <title canonical="false" TEIform="title">King James Version--Apocrypha</title>
        <type type="OSIS">Bible</type>
      </work>
    </header>
    <div canonical="false" type="book" osisID="PrMan" TEIform="div">
      <headCT TEIform="head">Prayer of Manasseh</headCT>
      <chapter osisID="PrMan.1" TEIform="div">
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.2">thou who hast made heaven and earth with all their order;</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.3">who hast shackled the sea by thy word of command, who hast confined the deep and sealed it with thy terrible and glorious name;</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.4">at whom all things shudder, and tremble before thy power,</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.5">for thy glorious splendor cannot be borne, and the wrath of thy threat to sinners is irresistible;</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.6">yet immeasurable and unsearchable is thy promised mercy,</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.7">for thou art the Lord Most High, of great compassion, long-suffering, and very merciful, and repentest over the evils of men. Thou, O Lord, according to thy great goodness hast promised repentance and forgiveness to those who have sinned against thee; and in the multitude of thy mercies thou hast appointed repentance for sinners, that they may be saved.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.8">Therefore thou, O Lord, God of the righteous, hast not appointed repentance for the righteous, for Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, who did not sin against thee, but thou hast appointed repentance for me, who am a sinner.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.9">For the sins I have committed are more in number than the sand of the sea; my transgressions are multiplied, O Lord, they are multiplied! I am unworthy to look up and see the height of heaven because of the multitude of my iniquities.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.10">I am weighted down with many an iron fetter, so that I am rejected because of my sins, and I have no relief; for I have provoked thy wrath and have done what is evil in thy sight, setting up abominations and multiplying offenses.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.11">And now I bend the knee of my heart, beseeching thee for thy kindness.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.12">I have sinned, O Lord, I have sinned, and I know my transgressions.</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.13">I earnestly beseech thee, forgive me, O Lord, forgive me! Do not destroy me with my transgressions! Do not be angry with me for ever or lay up evil for me; do not condemn me to the depths of the earth. For thou, O Lord, art the God of those who repent,</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.14">and in me thou wilt manifest thy goodness; for, unworthy as I am, thou wilt save me in thy great mercy,</verse>
        <verse canonical="true" osisID="PrMan.1.15">and I will praise thee continually all the days of my life. For all the host of heaven sings thy praise, and thine is the glory for ever. Amen.</verse>
      </chapter>
    </div>
  </osisText>
</osis>
